Guide to the Papers of the Association for the Relief of Respectable, Aged and Indigent Females in New York City 1813-1883 MS 801
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
Association for the Relief of Respectable, Aged and Indigent Females in New York City
1813-1883
MS 801
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
0.25 Linear feet (1 box)
Eight volumes of records of the Association for the Relief of Respectable Aged and Indigent Females in New York City which was formally established in February of 1814. From its beginning until 1838 the women of the Association met regularly and visited the dependent pensioners with gifts of clothing, groceries and cash. In 1838 they expanded their scope by establishing an asylum for the pensioners at 20th Street near 3rd Avenue. The NYC telephone directories reveal that they continued operating at an Amsterdam Avenue address until 1968.
Provenance
Purchased, January 1976.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Historical Note
Started in the fall of 1813 as a small association of women, the Society for the Relief of Indigent Respectable Females was formally established on February 14, 1814 in New York City. Intending to provide charity for a class of society they felt was neglected, the Society raised money largely through private donations to supply gifts of clothing, small stoves, and food for elderly women living in poverty. The Society was created out of religious obligation to a Christian ethic and continued to remain very close to the Christian faith throughout its history.
Beginning with only 16 managers under the First Directress Ann Dominick in 1814, the Society grew quickly and on March 10, 1815 was incorporated. As "a body corporate and politic" the Society became known by its now recognized name Association for the Relief of Respectable, Aged and Indigent Females. By 1838 the Board oversaw 4 other committees in addition to an Asylum built on 20th Street near 3rd Avenue to house and care for its "inmates," elderly female pensioners. The NYC telephone directories reveal that they continued operating at an Amsterdam Avenue address until 1968.
Scope and Content Note
The 8 volumes in this collection depict the meetings, responsibilities, and actions of the Advisory Committee, or Board, of the Association for the Relief of Respectable, Aged and Indigent Females in New York City. Though some gaps in years do appear between the volumes, there are included meeting minutes, expenditure books, and records of the pensioners for whom the Association cared. Also included are records of the Advisory Committee's visits to their Asylum during the years immediately following its construction in 1838. The volumes are arranged chronologically within each series.
Arrangement
The 8 volumes of this collection are arranged into two series:
Series I: Association Minutes and Expenditures
Series II: Pensioner and Asylum Records
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
The Constitution and Annual Reports of the Association for the Relief of Respectable, Aged and Indigent Females are located in the New-York Historical Society's General Collections.
Association for the Relief of Respectable Aged Indigent Females; Gray, A.; Innes, Anne; Accounts.; Charities -- New York (State) -- New York.; Journals (notebooks); Minutes.; New York (N.Y.); New York (N.Y.) -- Social conditions -- 19th century.; Older women -- New York (State) -- New York.; Poor women -- New York (State) -- New York.; Women in charitable work -- New York (State) -- New York.
- Subseries I.1: Minutes of the Board of Trustees - Volumes
  Scope and Contents note
  This subseries consists of Minutes of the Board of Trustees 1853-1951, bound in volumes, arranged chronologically. The first volume in the series briefly chronicles annual meetings 1854-1894. The following volumes contain the minutes of all meetings of the Board of Trustees, including annual meetings, monthly meetings, and special meetings 1853-1951. A volume of Minutes 1869-1879 from the Finance Committee, a subcommittee of the Board, is interfiled chronologically with the other board minutes. There is some duplication of information in volumes 3-5.
  - Minutes of the Ladies Society for the Relief of RIAF, 1814-1817 (Volume 2)
  - Receipts/Account Book of Extra Fuel for "Inmates", 1849-1862 (Volume 6)
  - Minutes of Advisory Committee Meetings, 1867-1870 (Volume 7)
  - Minutes of Advisory Committee Meetings, 1870-1883 (Volume 8)
- Series II: Pensioners and Asylum Records
  This series includes lists of pensioners visited by members of the association prior to the opening of the asylum, which contains the date of the entry, pensioners' names, pensioners' religious denomination, name of the member caring for them, remarks, and the date of pensioners' death if no longer living. Also in this series is a list of deaths at the asylum from its opening in 1838. Additionally included are notes made by members of the association recording the condition of the asylum during weekly visits.
  - List of Pensioners, 1813-1832 (Volume 1)
  - List of Deaths at the Asylum, 1838-1875 (Volume 3)
  - Weekly Visiting Committee's Book, 1839-1843 (Volume 4)
  - List of Out Door Pensioners, 1844-1860 (Volume 5)